Guide to the James Duane Livingston III Family Papers 1718-1999 MS 3144
New-York Historical Society
James Duane Livingston III family papers
1718-1999
New-York Historical Society
Livingston, James D., 1930-
MS 3144
1.25 Linear feet (in 3 document boxes).
Family history narratives, vital records, photographs, and genealogical research documenting the ancestry of James Duane Livingston III (1930-2019), a descendant on his father's side from Robert Livingston (1654-1728), first lord of Livingston Manor on the Hudson River, and on his mother's side from the Boullee family, German immigrants to New Hamburg, Ontario, Canada, in the mid-19th century.
Arrangement
The collection came to the New-York Historical Society in seven three-ring binders assembled by James Duane Livingston III. With minor exceptions (e.g., moving duplicate photographs from front or back binder pockets to join other copies in folders), the original order of the documents has been retained. Livingston supplied distinct titles for each binder, which the archivist has transferred to the following series titles:
Series I
"Old Family Manuscripts (indentures, estates, etc.)," 1718, 1810-1866
Series II
"Ancestors & Siblings (Aunt Patsy, Uncle Bob) of James D. Livingston Jr. (1890–1956)," 1872-1999
Series III
"James Duane Livingston Jr. (1890–1956)," 1889-1999
Series IV
"James Duane Livingston III (1930–[2019])," part one, 1930-1987
Series V
"James Duane Livingston III (1930–[2019])," part two, 1965-1970
Series VI
"Ancestors of Florence Boullee Livingston: Jugneits, Schmidlings, Boullees, Engelhardts," 1786-1999
Series VII
"Florence Josephine Boullee Livingston (1892–1983) & her brother William H. Boullee (1894–1955)," 1892-1983
Biographical / Historical
James Duane Livingston III (1930–2019) assembled this collection of family papers, photographs, and genealogical research to preserve for his daughters the biographical details of his own life, and of the lives of their shared ancestors and collateral relatives. On his father's side Livingston descended from Robert Livingston (1654–1728), his six-times great-grandfather, first lord of Livingston Manor, a 160,000-acre patent on the Hudson River. The Livingston family counted such notables as Robert R. Livingston (1746–1813), a member of the Committee of Five who drafted the Declaration of Independence, and Philip Livingston (1714–1778), who signed it. William Livingston (1723–1790) signed the U.S. Constitution, and Robert R. Livingston administered the oath of office to George Washington when he assumed the presidency in 1789. James Duane Livingston (1786–1837), a great-great grandson of the first lord of Livingston Manor, was the first to bear that combination of names. They would repeat in his grandson, James Duane Livingston (1859–1936), great-grandson, James Duane Livingston Jr. (1890–1956), and great-great-grandson, James Duane Livingston III, the compiler. (The suffixes "Jr." and "III" are not observed consistently on documents in the collection.)
James Duane Livingston Jr., a native of Indianapolis, married Florence Josephine Boullee (1892–1983), a native of New Jersey, in 1924 in New York City. Together they operated a printing concern on Wall Street. Florence descended from Wilhelm Heinrich Boullee (1821–1882), a country doctor, and his wife, Augusta E. Engelhardt (1827–1898), German immigrants who settled in New Hamburg, Ontario, Canada, in the 1840s, and from Friedrich Jugneit (1837–1901), a Prussian immigrant who served in the Union Army during the Civil War, and his wife, Maria Schmidling (1846– ).
Together James Duane and Florence (Boullee) Livingston had one child, a son, James Duane Livingston III, who was born in Brooklyn. James was a graduate of Midwood High School who went on to Cornell and Harvard Universities and spent thirty-three years as a research physicist for General Electric in Schenectady, New York. He married twice, first (1953) to Nancy Lee Clark, by whom he had three daughters (Joan, Susan, and Barbara Livingston), and second (1985) to Sherry (Hood) Penney (1937–2019).
____________________
This note is drawn from documents and narratives in the collection, and from family trees compiled by Howland Davis and Arthur Kelly in A Livingston Genealogical Register (Rhinebeck, N.Y.: Kinship, 1995).
Access Restrictions
Open to qualified researchers.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Susan Livingston, 2019, (accession no. MS-2019-042).
Scope and Contents
Items in the collection span the years 1718 through 1999 and include
• Assorted documents pertaining to the estate of Robert Cambridge Livingston (1742-1794), indentures and property records of his son, James Duane Livingston (1786-1837), and the title to property belonging to James's son, Charles James Livingston (1821-1871). Includes an early manuscript "Livingston Family Genealogy." (See Series I.)
• Material documenting the ancestry of James Duane Livingston Jr. (1890–1956) and his siblings, Gertrude Channing (Livingston) Kittredge Eaton (1892–1988), and Robert Teviot Livingston (1896–1968). Includes family history narratives, charts, vital records, newspaper obituaries, photographs, and an antique lace handkerchief. (See Series II.)
• Vital, school, and military records of James Duane Livingston Jr. (1890–1956), with two family history narratives by his son. (See Series III.)
• Autobiographical documents of James Duane Livingston III, including a number of grammar and high school report cards, school essays and stories, letters from his first wife, Nancy Lee Clark, and clippings on his career in metallurgy and ceramics research at General Electric. (See Series IV.)
• Additional autobiographical material of James Duane Livingston III, documenting his passion for tennis, his efforts to preserve the Glen Sanders Mansion, a historic house in Scotia, Schenectady County, New York, and his involvement with the Glenville Democratic Committee (also in Schenectady County), and two runs for a Glenville town council seat. (See Series V.)
• Documentation of the German-immigrant ancestry of James Duane Livingston III's mother, Florence Josephine (Boullee) Livingston (1892–1983). Includes a number of baptism, confirmation, and marriage certificates, as well as a series of letters from Friedrich Jugneit (1837–1901) to his daughter, Emily Charlotte (Jugneit) Boullee (1866–1957). With several narratives illustrating the relationships among the Boullee, Engelhardt, Jugneit, and Schmidling families. (Series VI.)
• Biographical documentation of James Duane Livingston III's mother, Florence Josephine (Boullee) Livingston (1892–1983) and her sole sibling, William Henry August Boullee (1894–1955). Includes Florence's baptism and confirmation certificates, her early driver's license, wedding photographs, and awards from the American Legion Auxiliary. William Boullee is represented by a few World War I service records, an end-of-life letter to his sister, and an obituary. (See Series VII.)
A number of James Duane Livingston III's autobiographical and family history narratives scattered throughout the collection shed light on the gathered documents:
• "My Grandparents" [paternal] (Box 1, Folder 16)
• "Ancestors of James Duane Livingston, Jr. (1890-1956), Gertrude Channing Livingston (b. 1892), and Robert Teviot Livingston (1896-1968)" (Box 1, Folder 18)
• "Ancestors and Descendants of James Duane Livingston 1786-1837" (Box 1, Folder 19)
• "Dad" (Box 1, Folder 54)
• "James D. Livingston Jr. (1890-1956) in World War I" (Box 2, Folder 3)
• "Mom & Dad & Me" (Box 2, Folder 13)
• "JDL3 and Tennis" (Box 2, Folder 56)
• "Travels and Travails of Friedrich Jugneit (1837-1901)" (Box 3, Folder 5)
• "My Grandparents" [maternal] (Box 3, Folder 6)
• "Letters from Friedrich [Jugneit]" (Box 3, Folder 16)
• "Wilhelm and Augusta Boullee of New Hamburg, Ontario, and their descendants" (Box 3, Folder 24)
Baptismal certificates; Birth certificates; Clippings (information artifacts); Confirmations (religious ceremonies); Death certificates; Genealogies (histories); Handkerchiefs; Letters (correspondence); Marriage certificates; Medals.; Military records.; Phonograph records; Photographs.; Report cards.; Vital statistics records; Glenville (N.Y.: Town); New Hamburg (Ont.); New York (State) -- Genealogy.; Boullee (Family); Livingston (Family)
- Series I. "Old Family Manuscripts (indentures, estates, etc.)", 1718, 1810-1866
  Scope and Contents
  Assorted documents pertaining mainly to the estate of Robert Cambridge Livingston (1742-1794), indentures and property records of his son, James Duane Livingston (1786-1837), and the title to property belonging to James's son, Charles James Livingston (1821-1871), great-grandfather of James Duane Livingston III. Includes an undated, but early, manuscript "Livingston Family Genealogy" (see Box 1, Folder 2).
  Arrangement
  With the exception of the Fauconnier letter in Box 1, Folder 14, which was originally framed, the documents in Series I are sorted in the order imposed by James Duane Livingston III.
  - [Title page and partial index], undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Livingston Family Genealogy, undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - [Indenture between Egbert Benson, et al., executors of the will of Robert C. Livingston, and James Duane Livingston], 1810 August 13 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - [Bond mortgage receipts of payments by William Miller to James Duane Livingston], 1812-1825 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Field Book of the 8th Section on the West Side of the Seneca Lake in James Watsons' purchase in the County of Steuben in the State of New York Belonging to J. D. Livingston, Esqr., New York, 1811-1818 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - [Joseph Grooms vs. James D. Livingston and others. Mortgage foreclosure, Columbia County, N.Y.], 1832 June 15 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - [Indenture between James D. Livingston and Asahel Blackman, Columbia County, New York], 1832 August [?] (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - [Indenture between James D. Livingston and Hiram Lapham, Columbia County, New York], 1835 September 24 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Surrogate's Court. In the matter of the final settlement of the accounts of the administrator(s) and administratrix of James Duane Livingston. Account, 1837 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Administrators of James D. Livingston to Mary R. Livingston. Assignment of contracts, 1839 February 19 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Abstract of the Title of Charles J. Livingston to House and lot known as No. 110 West 11th Street, New York City, [1858] (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - R. H. Walworth letter to Charles A. Peabody [typed transcription], 1866 November 5 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Letter of Attorney. Mary Livingston to Walter C. Livingston, 1835 November 19 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - [Pierre] Fauconnier letter, 1718 April 18 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    Conservation note
    This item was not originally included in Series I (i.e., Binder 1). The archivist placed it here for lack of a more obvious location. It came to the New-York Historical Society in a deteriorated frame. Conservation staff removed the item, sealed it in Mylar, and discarded the frame.
- Series II. "Ancestors & Siblings (Aunt Patsy, Uncle Bob) of James D. Livingston Jr. (1890–1956)", 1872-1999
  Material documenting the ancestry of James Duane Livingston Jr. (1890–1956) and his siblings, Gertrude Channing (Livingston) Kittredge Eaton (1892–1988), a.k.a. "Aunt Patsy," and Robert Teviot Livingston (1896–1968), a.k.a. "Uncle Bob." Includes family history narratives, charts, vital records, newspaper obituaries, photographs, and an antique lace handkerchief, a Livingston heirloom passed from Mabel Channing (Wright) Livingston to her daughter-in-law, Florence (Boullee) Livingston (see Box 1, Folder 28).
  With the exception of loose photographs moved from front or back binder pockets to join duplicates inside folders, the documents in Series II are sorted in the order imposed by James Duane Livingston III.
  - [Title page], undated (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - James Duane Livingston III. "My Grandparents" [paternal], 1999 August 25 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Paternal Ancestry of James Duane Livingston III [fan chart], undated (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - "Ancestors of James Duane Livingston, Jr. (1890-1956), Gertrude Channing Livingston (b. 1892), and Robert Teviot Livingston (1896-1968)", 1978 January (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - "Ancestors and Descendants of James Duane Livingston 1786-1837", 1983 July 2 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - [Correspondence re: Gilbert Stuart portraits of Walter and Hannah (Smith) Channing], 1995 November (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Death certificate [certified copy] of Fannie Rosalie Pell Wright (1848-1892), 1980 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Death certificate [certified copy] of David Wright (1806-1897), 1979 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - W. Mosby Williams letter to Fanny Rosalie Pell Wright, 1891 December 17 (Box 1, Folder 23)
    Includes a partially filled-in genealogical form and a copy of Frank Wright's obituary from "The Harvard Graduates' Magazine," December 1903, p. 286.
  - Frank Wright letter to daughter Mabel Channing Wright, 1892 March 21 (Box 1, Folder 24)
    With transcription.
  - James Duane Livingston letter to Bayard Tuckerman, [circa 1892] (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - William F. Channing letter to James Duane Livingston, 1893 July 27 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Wolcott Gibbs letter to James Duane Livingston, [1892?] March 29 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - [Lace handkerchief given by Mabel Channing (Wright) Livingston to Florence (Boullee) Livingston], undated (Box 1, Folder 28)
    With presentation letter dated Christmas 1950.
  - [James Duane Livingston confirmation certificate], 1872 April 1 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - [James Duane Livingston memorial service program], 1936 November 5 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - [Charles J. Livingston estate], [1896?] (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - [James Duane Livingston biographical material], 1936, undated (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - [James Duane Livingston home, Lexington, Kentucky], undated (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - [James Duane Livingston obituary], [1936 May] (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - [Charlotte Lucia Livingston photograph and obituary], undated, 1922 (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - [James Duane Livingston photographs and tributes], 1936, undated (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Franklin D. Roosevelt letters (2) to James Duane Livingston, 1931 April 21, May 4 (Box 1, Folder 37)
    Signed, as governor, on State of New York Executive Chamber stationery.
  - [Minna Swift Livingston bequests], [circa 1936] (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - [Mabel Channing (Wright) Livingston theatrical and musical performances], 1901-1905 (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - [Livingston signatures on birch bark, "Merry Mount"], 1906 August 26 (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - Second Season, Mrs. James Duane Livingston's "Garden-Home," Barnstable, Cape Cod., Mass., 1920 (Box 1, Folder 41)
  - [James Duane and Mabel Channing (Wright) Livingston marriage invitation, certificate, announcement, and 40th anniversary], 1889, 1929 (Box 1, Folder 42)
  - [James Duane Livingston family snapshot], undated (Box 1, Folder 43)
  - [Mabel Channing (Wright) Livingston photographs], undated (Box 1, Folder 44)
  - [Gertrude Channing (Livingston) Kittredge Eaton newspaper clippings], 1980, 1985 (Box 1, Folder 45)
  - [Gertrude Channing (Livingston) Kittredge Eaton photographs], 1981 January; 1982 July (Box 1, Folder 46)
  - Gertrude Kittredge Eaton. "Reminiscences of St. Paul's School", 1983 (Box 1, Folder 47)
  - [Henry Crocker Kittredge biographical material], 1967, undated (Box 1, Folder 48)
  - [Robert Teviot Livingston retirement dinner program and newspaper clipping], 1965 May 6, undated (Box 1, Folder 49)
  - [Robert Teviot Livingston obituary], 1968 January 8 (Box 1, Folder 50)
  - [Loose photographs from front binder pocket], undated (Box 1, Folder 51)
  - [Loose photographs from back binder pocket], undated (Box 1, Folder 52)
- Series III. "James Duane Livingston Jr. (1890–1956)", 1889-1999
  Vital, school, and military records of James Duane Livingston Jr. (1890–1956), with two family history narratives by his son: "Dad" (1990 January) and "James D. Livingston Jr. (1890-1956) in World War I" (1999 June). In 1932, for the celebrations surrounding the bicentennial of George Washington's birth, Livingston—in costume as his forebear, Robert R. Livingston (1746–1813)—administered the oath of office to an actor dressed as Washington in a reenactment of the first presidential inauguration (see the photograph and clippings in Box 2, Folder 7).
  With the exception of loose photographs moved from the back binder pocket to join duplicates inside folders, the documents in Series III are sorted in the order imposed by the James Duane Livingston III.
  - [Title page], undated (Box 1, Folder 53)
  - "Dad." [Family history narrative by James Duane Livingston III], 1990 January (Box 1, Folder 54)
  - [Livingston family bible records], 1889-1917 (Box 1, Folder 55)
  - [James Duane Livingston Jr. birth certificates (certified copies of 1926)], 1890 (Box 1, Folder 56)
  - [James Duane Livingston Jr. birth announcement telegram], 1890 February 15 (Box 1, Folder 57)
  - [James Duane Livingston Jr. cabinet card photographs] (3 folders), [circa 1890-1893] (Box 1, Folder 58-60)
  - [James Duane Livingston Jr. photographs], circa 1891-1905 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - [James Duane Livingston Jr. school records], 1904-1909 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - James D. Livingston III. "James D. Livingston Jr. (1890-1956) in World War I", 1999 June (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - [James Duane Livingston Jr. military records], 1914-1918 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Richard E. Byrd letter to James D. Livingston Jr. re: Byrd Antarctic Expedition, 1928 August 29 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - [James Duane Livingston Jr. photographs], undated (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - [George Washington Bicentennial Commission], 1932 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - [James Duane Livingston Jr. Air Warden Service discharge], 1945 June 30 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - [James Duane Livingston Jr. obituaries and business cards], 1956, undated (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - [James Duane Livingston Jr. death certificate], 1956 March [29] (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - [Loose photographs from front binder pocket], undated (Box 2, Folder 11)
- Series IV. "James Duane Livingston III (1930–[2019])," part one, 1930-1987
  Autobiographical documents of James Duane Livingston III, including a number of grammar and high school report cards, a series of school essays and stories, letters from his first wife, Nancy Lee Clark, and clippings on his career in metallurgy and ceramics research at General Electric.
  With the exception of loose photographs moved from the front binder pocket to join duplicates inside folders, the documents in Series IV are sorted in the order imposed by the James Duane Livingston III.
  - [Title page], undated (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - "Mom & Dad & Me." [Family history narrative by James Duane Livingston III], 1999 September 5 (Box 2, Folder 13)
    Although in an introductory note James Duane Livingston III informs his daughters that "this latest installment runs up to my high school graduation in January 1947," the narrative ends with the death of his mother, Florence Josephine (Boullee) Livingston in July 1983.
  - [James Duane Livingston III birth announcement cards], 1930 June 23 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - [James Duane Livingston III baptism certificate], 1930 September 21 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - [James Duane Livingston III photographs] (2 folders), undated (Box 2, Folder 16-17)
  - [James Duane Livingston III grammar school autograph album leaves], 1943 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - [James Duane Livingston III Camp Saugatuck medal], 1941 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - [New York World's Fair record album], 1939 (Box 2, Folder 20)
    "My parents and I made this recording at the 1939 New York World's Fair."
    Restricted
    This phonograph record is restricted because of its fragility and because N-YHS lacks equipment on which to play it.
  - [P.S. 193 awards and graduation program], 1942-1943 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - James Duane Livingston III. "My Trip", [1938] (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - James Duane Livingston III. "The Livingston's Trip to Florida", [1939] (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - James Duane Livingston III. "Perilous Mission", undated (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - James Duane Livingston III. "The Rover", undated (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - James Duane Livingston III. Untitled boxing story 1, undated (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - James Duane Livingston III. Untitled boxing story 2, undated (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - James Duane Livingston III. "The Midnight Fire Alarm", undated (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - James Duane Livingston III. "They Warned Me" (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - [James Duane Livingston III. P.S. 193 report cards], 1940, 1942 (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - [James Duane Livingston III. P.S. 193 class photograph], 1943 January (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - [James Duane Livingston III. Photographs], 1938, undated (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - [James Duane Livingston III. Photographs], 1940s, undated (Box 2, Folder 33)
  - ["Monarch of Bermuda" cruise ephemera], 1937 September 3, 5 (Box 2, Folder 34)
  - [James Duane Livingston III. High school awards and medals], 1944-1946 (Box 2, Folder 35)
  - [James Duane Livingston III. Midwood High School report cards], 1944, 1947 (Box 2, Folder 36)
  - [James Duane Livingston III. Midwood High School commencement program], 1947 February 5 (Box 2, Folder 37)
  - [John Scheer World War II ephemera], [1940s] (Box 2, Folder 38)
  - [Program, dance recital by the pupils of Atkinson Studio of the Dance], 1945 June 15 (Box 2, Folder 39)
    James Duane Livingston III performed in the ballroom group.
  - [James Duane Livingston III. Piano playing programs, certificates, report cards], 1945-1946 (Box 2, Folder 40)
  - James Duane Livingston III. "Multiplying by Adding" [article for Midwood High School math/science magazine], 1947 January (Box 2, Folder 41)
  - [James Duane Livingston III. Cornell University], 1947-1952, 1966 (Box 2, Folder 42)
  - [James Duane Livingston III. Letters to parents], 1952, 1956 (Box 2, Folder 43)
  - [James Duane Livingston III. Harvard College commencement and master's degree diploma], 1953 June 11 (Box 2, Folder 44)
  - [James Duane Livingston III. National Science Foundation fellowship], 1954 (Box 2, Folder 45)
  - [James Duane Livingston III. Marriage to Nancy Lee Clark], 1953 June 27 (Box 2, Folder 46)
  - [Nancy Lee Clark. Letters to James Duane Livingston III], [1952?], 1954 (Box 2, Folder 47)
  - [Nancy Lee (Clark) Livingston. Wedding photograph], [1953 June] (Box 2, Folder 48)
  - [James Duane Livingston III and daughters. Photographs], undated (Box 2, Folder 49)
  - [James Duane Livingston III. Harvard College commencement (PhD)], 1956 June 14 (Box 2, Folder 50)
  - [James Duane Livingston III. General Electric research lab], 1956-1987 (Box 2, Folder 51)
  - [James Duane Livingston III. Engagement announcement to Sherry H. Penney], [1984] (Box 2, Folder 52)
  - [Clermont, Livingston Manor], 1986-1987 (Box 2, Folder 53)
  - [Loose photographs from front binder pocket], circa 1939-1952 (Box 2, Folder 54)
- Series V. "James Duane Livingston III (1930–[2019])," part two, 1965-1970
  Autobiographical material documenting James Duane Livingston III's passion for tennis, his efforts to preserve the Glen Sanders Mansion, a historic house in Scotia, Schenectady County, New York, and his involvement with the Glenville Democratic Committee (also in Schenectady County), and two runs for a Glenville town council seat.
  The documents in Series V are sorted in the order imposed by James Duane Livingston III.
  - [Title page], undated (Box 2, Folder 55)
  - James Duane Livingston III. "JDL3 and Tennis", undated (Box 2, Folder 56)
  - [James Duane Livingston III. Tennis 1], 1965 (Box 2, Folder 57)
  - [James Duane Livingston III. Tennis 2], 1960s-1982 (Box 2, Folder 58)
  - [James Duane Livingston III. Glen-Sanders Mansion], 1967-1969 (Box 2, Folder 59)
  - [James Duane Livingston III. Glenville Democratic Committee], 1963 (Box 2, Folder 60)